A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade, 2010-2022 (bulk 2018-2021)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade, 2010-2022 (bulk 2018-2021)
The Library of Virginia
53496
5.95 cu. ft. (17 boxes)
Virginia Secretary of Commerce and Trade
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
proprietary records closed
Acquisition Information
Transferred on 7 January 2022 and 12 January 2022 by the Office of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade, 1111 East Broad Street, 4th Floor, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
Biographical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties, compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now. The General Assembly in 1972 created six Secretariats positions initially. As government reorganized, that number fluctuated when government agencies expanded or consolidated.
The Secretary of Commerce and Trade oversees the economic, community, and workforce development of the Commonwealth. During the Administration of Governor Ralph Northam (2018-2022) thirteen agencies and boards reported to the Secretary of Commerce and Trade: Board of Accountancy, Department of Business Assistance, Department of Housing and Community Development, Department of Labor and Industry, Department of Minority Business Enterprise, Department of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Department of Professional and Occupational Regulation, Tobacco Indemnification and Community Revitalization Commission, Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Virginia Employment Commission, Virginia Housing Development Authority, Virginia Racing Commission, Virginia Resource Authority, and Virginia Tourism Corporation.
Esther Lee served as Secretary of Commerce and Trade from 2018 January - April. After she left Governor Northam appointed Brian Ball, who had served as Deputy Secretary, to Secretary of Commerce and Trade (2018-2022). John Begala served as Assistant Secretary of Commerce and Trade from 2020 November - 2022 January. Robby Demeria served as Deputy Secretary of Commerce and Trade for Technology from 2018 June - 2020 May. Angela Navarro served as Deputy Secretary of Commerce and Trade from 2018 May - 2020 September. Cassidy Rasnick served as Deputy Secretary of Commerce and Trade for Rural Economic Development 2018 February - 2022 January. Turner Widgen served as Special Assistant 2018 August - 2020 November and as Assistant Secretary of Commerce and Trade 2020 November - 2021 August.
Scope and Content
Records, 2010-2022 (bulk 2018-2021), of the Secretary of Commerce and Trade during the administration of Governor Ralph Northam (2018-2022). The collection is housed in 17 boxes and includes agendas, briefings, brochures, calendars, clippings, correspondence, financial statements, itineraries, memorandum, newsletters, notes, programs, publications, reports, surveys, and other documents.
The bulk of the collection are the files of Deputy Secretary Angela Navarro and Deputy Secretary Cassidy Rasnick (Rural Economic Development).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into seven (7) series:
Series I: General files, 2019-2021
Series II: Secretary Brian Ball, 2018-2020
Series III: Assistant Secretary John Begala, 2018-2022
Series IV: Deputy Secretary Robby Demeria, 2003-2020
Series V: Deputy Secretary Angela Navarro, 2013-2020
Series VI: Deputy Secretary Cassidy Rasnick, 2010-2021
Series VII: Assistant Secretary Turner Widgen, 2018-2021.
Contents List
- Series I: General files, 2019-2021., Extent: .35 cu. ft. (1 box). (Box 1)
  Series I: General files, 2019-2021, is housed in one box and is arranged alphabetically by folder title. Includes correspondence; materials relating to Covid-19, minimum wage, rent relief, and taxes.
  Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Covid-19, Number Seventy-Two (2020) and Public Health Emergency Nine, 2020 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Covid-19, Mitigation proposals (Forward Virginia), 2020-2021 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Dept. of Energy, Reenergize Southwest, 2021 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dept. of Planning and Budget, Dept. of Housing and Community Development Decision Packages, 2021 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minimum wage, 2019-2020 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Office of Outdoor Recreation, ca. 2020 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Small business recovery, ca. 2020-2021 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Unitary Combined Corporate Income Tax Reporting, 2021 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - University of Virginia, Attracting Remote Workers to Rural Virginia, 2021 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Innovation Partnership Authority (VIPA) - Center for Innovative Technology (CIT), Meeting, 2021 September (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Rent Relief Program, 2021 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II: Secretary Brian Ball, 2018-2020., Extent: .60 cu. ft. (1 1/2 boxes). (Box 2-3)
  Series II: Secretary Brian Ball, 2018-2020, is housed in one and a half boxes and is arranged alphabetically by folder title. Includes correspondenceare
  - Genedge, 2018 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - International Trade Plan, 2019 (Box 2, Folder 2-6)
  - Project Grape, 2020 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Trade, 2018 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Project Cooper, 2018 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Series III: Assistant Secretary John Begala, 2018-2022., Extent: .25 cu. ft. (1/2 box). (Box 3)
  Series III: Assistant Secretary John Begala, 2018-2022, is housed in one half box and is arranged alphabetically by folder title. Includes correspondence
  - Correspondence, 2018-2022 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Dept. of Energy, Reenergize Southwest, 2021 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - General, 2020-2021 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - General, 2021 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Notes, ca. 2018-2022 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Deputy Secretary Robby Demeria, 2003-2020., Extent: .95 cu. ft. (3 boxes). (Box 4-6)
  Series IV: Deputy Secretary Robby Demeria is housed in three boxes and is arranged alphabetically by folder title. Includes correspondence
  - Broadband, Commonwealth Connect Plan, 2018 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Center for Innovative Technology (CIT)- Virginia Innovative Partnership Authority (VIPA), Commonwealth Research and Technology Strategic Roadmap, 2019 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - CIT-VIPA, Innovation, Commercialization, and Entrepreneurship in the Commonwealth, 2018 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - CIT-VIPA, Innovation and Entrepreneurship Investment Authority Act, 2018 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - CIT-VIPA, Meetings, 2018 September-December (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - CIT-VIPA, Partnership for Innovation and Entrepreneurship Authority (PIE), 2018-2020 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
  - CIT-VIPA, Virginia Innovation Report, 2019 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - CIT-VIPA, Virginia Smart Communities Working Group, 2018 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - CIT-VIPA, 757 Angels, 2019 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - CIT-VIPA, Virginia Information Technologies Agency Presentation, 2018 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Dept. of Housing and Community Development, Budget, 2018-2020 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - GO Virginia, 2019 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 2018-2020 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Misclassification and Payroll fraud, 2018-2019 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Small, Woman- and Minority- Owned Businesses (SWaM), 2003-2020 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Employment Commission, 2018 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, 2019 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Series V: Deputy Secretary Angela Navarro, 2018-2021., Extent: 1.4 cu. ft. (4 boxes). (Box 7-10)
  Series V: Deputy Secretary Angela Navarro is housed in four boxes and is arranged alphabetically by folder title. Includes correspondence
  - Agency head meetings, 2019 March-May (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Boards, 2019-2020 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Dept. of Housing and Community Development, Cash proffers, 2016-2019 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Dept. of Housing and Community Development, Fire programs, 2019 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Dept. of Housing and Community Development, Governor Coordinating Council on Homelessness, 2018 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Dept. of Housing and Community Development, Meetings, 2018 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Dept. of Housing and Community Development, Presentation, ca. 2019 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Atlantic Coast Pipeline, 2014-2015 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Atlantic Coast Pipeline, 2016-2018 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Atlantic Coast Pipeline, Dept. Game and Inland Fisheries, 2016 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Atlantic Coast Pipeline, Mitigation, 2013-2016 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Budget amendments, 2018 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Clean Energy, Executive Order No. 43, 2018-2019 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Coal Ash, 2016-2019 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Coastal Resilience Laboratory and Accelerator Center, 2016 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Combined Heat and Power, 2018 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Dong Energy, 2017 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Electric Vehicles, Volkswagen, 2016-2018 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Energy Performance Contract, 2019 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Energy Policy, 2018 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Fracking, 2016-2017 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Governor's Clean Energy Workshop, 2018 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Mountain Valley Pipeline, 2015-2018 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Offshore drilling, 2014-2017 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Senate Bill 966 [Energy efficiency], 2018-2019 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Succession plan, 2018 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Transportation and Climate Initiative, 2018-2019 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Virginia Clean Cities, 2018 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Virginia Energy Plan, 2018 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Virginia Offshore Wind Development Authority, 2017-2018 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, Virginia Offshore Wind Development Authority, 2018-2019 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Dept. of Professional and Occupational Regulation, 2018 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Gaming, 2018 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Gateway to Werowocomoco, 2018 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Governor's Advisory Council on Environmental Justice, 2017-2018 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Memorandum, 2020 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Pamunkey Tribe casino, 2018-2019 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - RISE Resillence Innovations, Meeting, 2018 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Secretary of Natural Resources, 2015-2016 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Small Business and Supplier Diversity, 2018-2019 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Small, Women, and Minority-Owned Businesses, 2019 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Dept. of Transportation, Transportation Partnership Opportunity Fund, 2018 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, 2018-2019 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Housing Development Authority, Executive Order 25, 2018-2019 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Housing Development Authority, 2018-2019 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Housing Development Authority, REACH Virginia Funds, 2019-2020 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Impact Investing, 2018-2019 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Land Conservation, 2018 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Racing Commission, Historical horse racing, 2018 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Research Investment Committee, 2018 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Tourism Corporation, 2018 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Workforce Development, 2018-2019 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Series VI: Deputy Secretary Cassidy Resnick, 2010-2021., Extent: 2.45 cu. ft. (7 boxes). (Box 11-17)
  Series VI: Deputy Secretary Cassidy Resnick, 2018-2022, is housed in seven boxes and is arranged alphabetically by folder title. Includes correspondence
  - Board appointments, 2018-2019 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Broadband, 2017-2018 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Broadband, Commonwealth Connect, 2018 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Broadband, Commonwealth Connect, 2019 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Broadband, Commonwealth Connect, 2020 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Broadband, Feasibility report, 2018 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Broadband, Virginia Tobacco Region, 2016-2018 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Budget, 2019 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Budget, 2019 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
  - Budget, 2020 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Camp Tour of Virginia State Parks, 2019 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - COVID-19, Beaches, 2020 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - CODIV-19, Safer at home, 2020 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Craft Beer Month, 2018-2019 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Data Center Coalition, 2019 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Dept. of Housing and Community Development, Budget, 2018-2019 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Dept. of Housing and Community Development, Grants, 2018 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Dept. of Housing and Community Development, Opportunity Zones, 2018 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Dept. of Housing and Community Development, Virginia Growth and Opportunity Board, 2018-2021 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Dept. of Mines, Minerals and Energy, 2018 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Event briefing information, Miscellaneous, 2019 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Goals, 2017-2018 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - GO Virginia, 2018 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - GO Virginia, 2019 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - HB 222, 2018-2019 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - JLARC, Report, 2017-2018 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Legislation, 2019 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 2018-2020 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Office of the State Inspector General, 2016-2019 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Opportunity Zone Marketplace, 2019 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Outdoor Retailer Summer Market, 2019 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - PACED, 2018 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Partnership for Innovation, Entrepreneurship, and Research, 2019 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Policies, 2020 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Rebrand, ca. 2018 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Speeches (drafts), 2019 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Board of Workforce Development, 2018 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Dept. of Labor and Industry, 2018 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, 2017-2018 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, 2018 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, 2018-2019 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Amazon headquarters, 2018 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Commonwealth Center for Advanced Manufactory (CCAM), 2018 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Commonwealth Center for Advanced Manufactory (CCAM), 2019 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Economic Development Strategic Plans, 2010-2018 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Effectiveness of Economic Development Incentive Grant Programs, 2018 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Major Employment and Investment Projects (MEI), 2017-2019 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Monogram Foods, 2018 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Rankings, 2019 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Rural Virginia, 2018 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Rural Virginia, 2019 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Tourism, 2017 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Weekly reviews, 2018 (Box 16, Folder 6-7)
  - Virginia Economic Development Partnership, Weekly reviews, 2018-2019 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Employment Commission, 2018 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Housing Development Authority, 2018 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Virginia Housing Development Authority, Housing, 2018-2019 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Virginia Innovation Partnership Authority (VIPA) - Center for Innovative Technology (CIT), 2018 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Research Investment Committee, 2018 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Small Business and Supplier Diversity, 2018 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Tourism Corporation, 2018-2020 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Wallops Island Regional Alliance, 2019-2020 (Box 17, Folder 6)
- Series VII: Assistant Secretary Turner Widgen, 2018-2021., Extent: .15 cu. ft. (1 folder). (Box 17)
  Series VII: Assistant Secretary Turner Widgen is housed in one folder and consists of two hand-written notebooks with meeting notes.
  - Handwritten notebooks, 2018-2021 (Box 17, Folder 7)